Guide to the Music Department Records, 1878-[ongoing]
Music Department Records, 1878-[ongoing]
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Music Dept.
1000-182
24.25
29
The music program at Wesleyan University dates back to the early days of the institution, when informal singing groups performed for special occasions. As the program expanded and became more formalized, courses were offered, and in 1929 the Music Department was established. Performance groups came to include the Glee Club, the Chapel Choir, the Choral Society, the Jibers, the Cardinals, the Wesleyan Band, and a number of instrumental ensembles. During the 1950s, associate professor David McAllester introduced world music courses into the curriculum, and in 1966 the department established a doctoral program in ethnomusicology. Visiting artists from various regions around the world, including Africa, India, Indonesia, Japan, and Korea, have performed at the university.
The collection includes proposals, meeting minutes, memoranda, correspondence, and reports relating to the establishment of the ethnomusicology doctoral program. It also contains photographs and printed material relating to music performances by faculty, student groups, and visiting world music artists. Materials in the Music Concert Programs, Concert Correspondence Files, Events Scrapbooks, and Programs and Records series have not been processed.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Series 1 materials given by David McAllester, August 1976. Series 2 received in 1990 from the Music Department. Other materials received in 1992, 1993, 2007 and at additional dates from the Music Department.
Historical Note
Music has been part of the Wesleyan University experience since the early days of the institution. Known as a "singing college," Wesleyan inherited a tradition of music from the hymnody of its Methodist roots (see David B. Potts's Wesleyan University, 1831-1910: Collegiate Enterprise in New England). The first music performances at the university were organized by volunteers and sponsored by groups such as the Middlesex Musical Association. Beginning in the 1840s, glee clubs were created for special occasions, and in 1862 Wesleyan singers had their first public tour. In 1882 the university hired a professional musician as glee club coach, and the group gave standing-room-only public appearances, including an 1888 concert at the Metropolitan Opera House in New York City. From the 1880s on, undergraduate students as well as alumni composed songs; these were collected in the Wesleyan Song Book, first published in 1901. Weekly sings took place on the chapel steps beginning in about 1901, and in about 1913 the university began offering a small stipend to students who participated in the chapel choir.
During the 1920s, the music program at Wesleyan became more formalized. In 1921, the Music and Dramatics Board was created to supervise musical and dramatic organizations and arrange concerts and trips. The university also offered its first course work in music. In the academic year 1925/26, Hugh L. Smith (class of 1915), an assistant professor in the Department of Romance Languages, offered a course on the history and appreciation of music. In 1928/29, courses in dramatic music and harmony were added. Then, in 1929, alumnus John Spencer Camp (class of 1878) donated a large sum to set up a chair of music at the university. Joseph Stephen Daltry was appointed to the newly endowed chair, and the Music Department was established.
The music program at Wesleyan continued to expand over the years. By the late 1940s, two professors--Joseph Daltry and George McManus--were offering about ten courses a year. In 1949, Richard Winslow (class of 1940) joined the staff. By the mid-1950s, singers performed not only with the Chapel Choir and Glee Club but also with the Choral Society, a male quartet called the Jibers, and a group of eight or nine called the Cardinals. The Wesleyan Band performed at football games and various campus affairs, and a woodwind and brass ensemble played several recitals a year. The Music Department, at that time housed in Judd Hall, had several sound-proof studios and an extensive collection of phonograph records. By the late 1960s, musical opportunities at the university included private lessons; the Wesleyan University concert series; the college orchestra, a "town-gown" organization; the Wesleyan String Quartet; and the Collegium Musicum, which performed medieval and Renaissance music.
A significant development in the music program that occurred around the middle of the twentieth century was the introduction of the study of music "as a universal phenomenon beyond the confines of Western European tradition" (Wesleyan University Bulletin, 1956/57). In 1956/57, associate professor David McAllester, an anthropologist whose specialty was the culture and music of the Navajo, first offered Music 31, Ethnic and Folk Music, in addition to the anthropology courses he taught in the Department of Psychology. In 1961, McAllester teamed up with Robert E. Brown, a specialist in the music of India, to teach classes in the university's new World Music Program. McAllester and Richard Winslow proposed an advanced program of study, and in 1966 the department began offering a doctorate in ethnomusicology in addition to undergraduate and master's degrees. By the 1970s, courses taught by resident and visiting members of the department's faculty covered Western classical, Afro-American, South Indian, North Indian, and Japanese music; the 1970/71 catalog listed some thirty-two courses and seminars in non-Western music. Study groups were organized focusing on the music of South India, Japan, Persia, Korea, and the Javanese gamelan.
In 1973, Wesleyan opened its Center for the Arts, a complex of eleven buildings housing undergraduate programs in art and art history, dance, theater, and music, as well as the graduate program in ethnomusicology. The Center comprises classrooms, galleries, and studios, and its music facilities include a recording studio, a computer and experimental music studio, Crowell Concert Hall, and World Music Hall.
The Music Department currently provides course work and performing opportunities in music from around the world. More than sixty courses are offered. A number of activities--including a variety of chamber ensembles and ensembles in Asian, African, American, and European traditions--are available to students. Music facilities include a collection of instruments from many different cultures; a music-instrument manufacturing workshop; a scores and recordings collection; and a world music archives. An ongoing departmental colloquium presents lectures on issues in the world of music by students, faculty, and outside speakers. In addition, the department sponsors events such as concerts by world-renowned jazz artists, the Wesleyan World Percussion Festival (2000), New England Gamelan Weekend (2002), the Celtic Routes Festival (2003), and the annual Navaratri Festival.
Collection Overview
The collection is arranged in six series. The records in Series 1, the Ethnomusicology Doctoral Program, relate to the establishment of the Music Department's advanced degree program in world music. The proposal drafts and notes, created in large part by David McAllester, describe the program and its requirements, including budget information. McAllester's proposal for an anthropology department, dating to roughly the same period, is also included. The meeting minutes, memoranda, correspondence, and grant proposals relate to the creation of the ethnomusicology doctoral program. An NDEA fellowship application and a report entitled Program for Advanced Studies in World Music are also included. The Creative Arts Program documents contain information on the ethnic music component of the music program.
Series 2, Photographs, comprises images and printed material relating to music performances by members of the Wesleyan community or artists visiting the university, circa 1947 to 1988. Approximately 400 print photographs--as well as contact sheets, negatives, and slides--are included. The photographs are arranged in two subseries: Faculty and Student Groups, and World Music Performers. The Faculty and Student Groups subseries includes images of Music Department staff and student music group members, either posed or during concerts. Photographs in the World Music Performers subseries show visiting artists who specialized in African, Indian, Indonesian, Japanese, Korean, and Native American music. Instruments shown include the Indian been, kanjira, mrdangam, sarangi, sarod, sitar, tabla, tambura, and vina; the Javanese gender and gamelan; and the Japanese koto, shakuhachi, and shamisen. Photographs of ethnic dance performances and Javanese shadow plays are also included. A third subseries, Printed Material, consists of biographies and resumes of world music performers. A fourth subseries, Oversized Material, includes a drawing of Professor Richard Winslow as well as programs and explanatory notes for world music performances.
Materials in Series 3, Music Concert Programs; Series 4, Concert Correspondence Files; Series 5, Events Scrapbooks; and Series 6, Programs and Records, have not been processed.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Curricula.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Music Dept.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Songs and music.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--World Music Institute.; Wesleyan Glee Club.; McAllester, David P. (David Park), 1916-2006.; Music--Africa.; Music--India.; Music--Indonesia.; Music--Japan.; Music--Korea.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1. Ethnomusicology Doctoral Program, circa 1960-1966
  The Ethnomusicology Doctoral Program records relate to the establishment of the Music Department's advanced degree program in world music. The proposal drafts and notes, created in large part by David McAllester, describe the program and its requirements, including budget information. McAllester's proposal for an anthropology department, dating to roughly the same period, is also included. The meeting minutes, memoranda, correspondence, and grant proposals relate to the creation of the ethnomusicology doctoral program. An NDEA fellowship application and a report entitled Program for Advanced Studies in World Music are also included. The Creative Arts Program documents contain information on the ethnic music component of the music program.
  - Proposal drafts and notes, circa 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anthropology Department proposal, after 1960 (Folder 2)
  - Meeting minutes, 14 May 1964-21 October 1964 (Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, 24 April 1964-10 November 1965 (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 22 November 1963-9 December 1965 (Folder 5)
  - Creative Arts Program, 2 November 1964-20 December 1965 (Folder 6)
  - Grant proposals, 1965-1966 (Folder 7)
  - NDEA Fellowship application, May 1966 (Folder 8)
  - Program for Advanced Studies in World Music report, circa 1966 (Folder 9)
  - Press release, 1966 (Folder 10)
- Series 2. Photographs, circa 1947-1988
  The Photographs series comprises images and printed material relating to music performances by members of the Wesleyan community or artists visiting the university, circa 1947 to 1988. Approximately 400 print photographs--as well as contact sheets, negatives, and slides--are included. The photographs are arranged in two subseries: Faculty and Student Groups, and World Music Performers. The Faculty and Student Groups subseries includes images of Music Department staff and student music group members, either posed or during concerts. Photographs in the World Music Performers subseries show visiting artists who specialized in African, Indian, Indonesian, Japanese, Korean, and Native American music. Instruments shown include the Indian been, kanjira, mrdangam, sarangi, sarod, sitar, tabla, tambura, and vina; the Javanese gender and gamelan; and the Japanese koto, shakuhachi, and shamisen. Photographs of ethnic dance performances and Javanese shadow plays are also included. A third subseries, Printed Material, consists of biographies and resumes of world music performers. A fourth subseries, Oversized Material, includes a drawing of Professor Richard Winslow as well as programs and explanatory notes for world music performances.
  - Faculty and Student Groups
    Folders are arranged alphabetically.
    - Joel Andrews? (harp), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - B. Brown [Robert Brown], undated (Folder 2)
    - The Cardinals, 1951-1958 and undated (Folder 3)
    - Delta Tau Delta informal, undated (Folder 4)
    - Glee Club concerts in church, 1965-1968 and undated (Folder 5)
    - Theodore C. Grame, November 1969 (Folder 6)
    - Sydney Griller and Jack O'Brien, undated (Folder 7)
    - Instrumental Ensemble, undated (Folder 8)
    - The Jibers, 1952-1959 (Folder 9)
    - Julliard String Quartet, undated (Folder 10)
    - Memorial Chapel concerts, 1959-1988 and undated (Folder 11)
    - Music Department, 1957-1961 and undated (Folder 12)
    - Music section of the Humanities Laboratory, undated (Folder 13)
    - Olla Podrida, undated (Folder 14)
    - Ray Rendall, May 1958 and undated (Folder 15)
    - Smith College/Wesleyan University Concert Choir, circa 1958-1963 (Folder 16)
    - String instruments, circa 1956 and undated (Folder 17)
    - Unidentified group at airport, undated (Folder 18)
    - Wesleyan Band, undated (Folder 19)
    - Wesleyan Choral Society, 1955-1956 (Folder 20)
    - Wesleyan Chorus, 1956 (Folder 21)
    - Wesleyan Glee Club, 1947-1967 and undated (Folder 22)
    - Wesleyan Orchestra and Chamber Orchestra, 1956-1957 and undated (Folder 23)
    - Richard K. Winslow, 1957-1965 and undated (Folder 24)
      One drawing is located with Oversized Material in Box 6.
  - World Music Performers
    - Africa
      Performers include Emmanuel Duodu, Christian Darkwa, and Abraham Adzenyah.
      - African dance, circa 1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - African drumming, circa 1972 and undated (Folder 2)
      - African wind instrument, undated (Folder 3)
      - Emmanuel Duodu (dance)--West Africa, undated (Folder 4)
    - India
      - Ravi Shankar, undated (Folder 5)
      - Jon Higgins--South India, undated (Folder 6)
      - Ranganathan (mrdangam) and unidentified performer (tambura)--North India, circa 1968 and undated (Folder 7)
      - Tewari (vocal), Srinivasan (tambura), and Zia Mohiuddin Dagar (been)--North India, circa 1968 and undated (Folder 8)
      - Raghu (mrdangam), Viswanathan (flute), Srinivasan (tambura), and unidentified performer (violin)--South India, undated (Folder 9)
      - Viswanathan (flute)--India, undated (Folder 10)
      - Ranganathan (mrdangam), Viswanathan (flute), Srinivasan (tambura), and unidentified performers (kanjira and violin)--South India, undated (Folder 11)
      - Kalyanakrishna (vina) and Muthulakshmi (vina), circa 1968-1971 and undated (Folder 12)
      - Nageswara Rao (vina), circa 1966 and undated (Folder 13)
      - Krishna Sanyal (sitar), undated (Folder 14)
      - S. Ramanathan (vina), undated (Folder 15)
      - Ramnad V. Raghavan--South India, circa 1970 and undated (Folder 16)
      - L. Shamkar (violin)--South India, 1973 and undated (Folder 17)
      - Sharda Sahai (tabla) and Ram Chakravarty (sitar)--North India, undated (Folder 18)
      - Ram Narayan (sarangi), undated (Folder 19)
      - Debu Chaudhuri (sitar) and Sitaram Sharma (tabla), undated (Folder 20)
      - Mahapurush Misra (tabla), 1966 and undated (Folder 21)
      - Dagar (sarod)--North India, undated (Folder 22)
      - Unidentified performer (violin)--South India, undated (Folder 23)
      - Unidentified performers (mrdangam, tambura, and violin), undated (Folder 24)
      - Unidentified performers (flute, tambura, and mrdangam), undated (Folder 25)
      - Unidentified performer (mrdangam), undated (Folder 26)
      - Unidentified performers (tabla, sitar, and tambura), undated (Folder 27)
    - Indonesia
      - Oemartopo, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Suharto (dance), undated (Folder 2)
      - Mrs. Suharti Soedarsono and Suharto, undated (Folder 3)
      - Mrs. Suharti Soedarsono, undated (Folder 4)
      - Robertus Soedarsono (dance)--Java, circa 1970 and undated (Folder 5)
      - Sumarsam and Urip Sri Maeny (dance), undated (Folder 6)
      - Endo Swanda, undated (Folder 7)
      - Prawotosaputro (gender)--Javanese gamelan, circa 1970 (Folder 8)
      - Javanese gamelan, undated (Folder 9)
    - Japan
      - Hiroka Abiru and Hirochika Nakajima, circa 1970 (Folder 10)
      - Kansuke Kawase, circa 1971 (Folder 11)
      - Mrs. Ayano Ichimura (koto), Miss Momoyo Kishibe, and Mr. Kansuke Kawase, undated (Folder 12)
      - Mrs. Ayano Ichimura (koto and shamisen), circa 1971 (Folder 13)
      - Mr. Jodo Tanaka, circa 1972 and undated (Folder 14)
      - Tanaka, Ichimura (shamisen), and Torii (koto), 1973 (Folder 15)
      - Namino Torii (shamisen and koto), circa 1966-1979 and undated (Folder 16)
      - Kazuyuki Takano (shamisen and koto), circa 1969 and undated (Folder 17)
      - Kodo Araki (shakuhachi), circa 1968 (Folder 18)
      - Student recital, 27 January 1971 (Folder 19)
      - Unidentified performers (flute), undated (Folder 20)
      - Unidentified performer (koto), undated (Folder 21)
    - Korea
      - Chae-Son Cho (flute), circa 1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Native American
      - Douglas Mitchell (drum), undated (deceased December 1972) (Folder 2)
    - Unidentified
      - Contact sheet, undated (Folder 3)
      - Negatives, 12 October 1969 and undated (Folder 4)
      - Photograph, undated (Folder 5)
      - Photographs (guitar), undated (Folder 6)
      - Slides, undated (Folder 7)
  - Printed Material
    Oversized printed material is located in Box 6.
    - World music performers' biographies and resumes, undated (Folder 8)
  - Oversized Material
    - Drawing of Richard K. Winslow, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - World music performance programs and explanatory notes, 1970-1971 (Folder 2)
- Series 3. Music Concert Programs, 1878-[ongoing]
  6 boxes (5.5 linear feet)
- Series 4. Concert Correspondence Files, 1935-1973
  1 box (0.5 linear feet)
- Series 5. Events Scrapbooks, 1944-1953 and 1958-1968
- Series 6. Programs and Records
  15 boxes (14.5 linear feet)